A Guide to the E. Vincent Cowdry papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff FA155
Rockefeller Archive Center
E. Vincent Cowdry papers, Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research Scientific Staff
undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Cowdry, E. V. (Edmund Vincent)
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
Rockefeller University
FA155
0.44 Cubic Feet 1 box
2½" letter box
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents
Business Manager Files
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 C838
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for research.
Cowdry, E. V. (Edmund Vincent); Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research; Rockefeller University
- Correspondence, 1921-1954; 1
  Scope and Contents
  Selected items of correspondence are described in this series.
  - 1921 January-June (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - E.V. Cowdry/S. Flexner, re arrival at PUMC (Peking Union Medical College), Peking w/ Encl: "Contributions from the Department of Anatomy, Peking Union Medical College of the Rockefeller Foundation", 1921 January 3
      - Volume 1, 1918-1920
      - Volume 2 (with the publisher), 1921-?
      - Program of monthly meetings of the "Anatomical and Anthropological Association of China" held at PUMC, 1920 October-1921 May 27
    - Exchange between S. Flexner, E.V. Cowdry, Miss von der Osten. and E. Bakaner re offer of appointment at RIMR for 2 years beginning July 1, 1921 and E.V. Cowdry's acceptance by cable Jan 31, 1921 and then by letter dated Feb 1, 1921, 1921 January 25-February 2
    - S. Flexner/E.B. Smith w/Encl: Draft of Feb 4, 1921 letter to Cowdry outlining conditions of RIMR appointment, 1921 February 4
    - S. Flexner/E.V. Cowdry. Carbon copy of final letter outlining conditions of RIMR appointment including added specific conditions, 1921 February 5
    - E.V. Cowdry/S. Flexner, accepts appointment as of July 1, 1921, 1921 March 12
  - 1922-circa 1924 June (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith, re Willie Masek, 1922 June 13
    - Exchange between E.V. Cowdry and S. Flexner re invitation by Sir Arnold Theiler to E.V. Cowdry to spend one year at Transvaal University College, Pretoria, 1923 October 22-1924 January 17
    - C.C. Williamson/S. Flexner w/attached clipping: 1923 Dec 29, The African World, "Sir Arnold Theiler's American Tour." [Letter written by Sir Arnold Theiler aboard "President Cleveland, " 26 Nov 1923], 1924 January 17
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith re William Masek, 1924 April 30
    - Estimate [of expenditures] covering period to June 30, 1924, Dr. Cowdry's expedition to South Africa, undated
    - JAMA [Journal of the American Medical Association] clipping, re Cowdry to South Africa, Transvaal University College, Pretoria, to study life cycle of protozoa causing diseases in domestic animals, 1924 May 24
  - 1924 July-December (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - E.B. Smith/Cowdry, re deferred annuity, apartment, Dr. Nicholson and Willie Masek, 1924 July 23
    - Cowdry/S. Flexner re Dr. du Toit, 1924 September 8
    - S. Flexner/Cowdry re Cowdry book "Cytology, " Rickettsia findings and report and Dr. du Toit, 1924 October 22
    - Exchange between Cowdry, S. Flexner and 1 item with Theobald Smith/S. Flexner re Cowdry's work on 'Rickettsia' includes 2 photographs of Rickettsia cells [in cases of Heartwater] and re Hans Theiler (Sir Arnold's son), 1924 September 29 1924 October 14 1924 November 15 1924 November 18 1924 November 26
    - Sir Arnold Theiler/S. Flexner, re Cowdry's success in study of Heartwater and Rickettsia and praise of Cowdry, 1924 November 5
    - S. Flexner/Sir Arnold Theiler, acknowledgment of Nov 5 letter and re Theobald Smith's willingness to appoint Sir Arnold Theiler's son, a Fellow, at RIMR Princeton, 1924 December 19
    - Exchange between E.V. Cowdry and Simon Flexner. re publication of following in JEM and Theiler's report in South Africa re discovery of Rickettsia, with approval of publication by S. Flexner and continuation of investigations by Cowdry in New York, 1924 November 11 1924 November 17 1924 December 19 1924 December 22
      Scope and Contents note
      Includes.
      - Part 1: Heartwater dealing with the Rickettsia in infected mammals
      - Part 2: Heartwater dealing with the Rickettsia in ticks
      - Part 3: Deals with certain microorganisms transmitted hereditarily in ticks and not associated with disease
  - 1925 January-1927 April (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith re return from South Africa, early March 1925, 1925 January 12
    - Cowdry/F. Stanley Howe, re William Masek, 1925 April 20
    - Howe/E.B. Smith re form letter, 12 June 1925, re Peking Union Medical College "Yu Wang Fu Association", 1925 June 16
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith re Dr. John Smith, 1925 June 30
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith re recommendation of Dr. Theodore Dunham by E.F. Du Bois, 20 June 1925 to Cowdry w/ E.B. Smith reply, 7 July 1925, 1925 July 1
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith re Miss Tilden's work, 1925 August 11
    - Cowdry/Dr. Blake, accepting appointment as Associate Member, RIMR, 1926 June 15
    - Exchange between Cowdry and E.B. Smith re "Thelco" incubator for Dr. Hughes' work at Woods Hole, 1926 July 1-14
    - Exchange between Dr. Cowdry, S. Flexner, Thoebald Smith and Business Manager re Cowdry's trip to Tunis to study the organism Anaplasmosis, 1926 December 7-1927 January 17
      Includes: Correspondence re request for travel expenses to Tunis and Cowdry's, "Estimate of Travel Expense of E.V. Cowdry to Tunis and Return" and statement re purpose of trip, "Objects of Proposed Expedition to Tunis" and approval of appropriations for equipment and travel by RIMR Bd of Sci Dirs.
    - Exchange between Simon Flexner, Colonial Secretary of Nairobi and J. Butler Wright, Assistant Secretary of State re invitation to Cowdry to study a parasitic development in ticks. Regrets, since Cowdry engaged in study of Anaplasmosis at the Pasteur Institute, in Tunis, 1927 February 11 1927 February 14 1927 February 23 1927 April 7; cables
  - 1927 June-1930 March, 1953, 1954 January (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Exchange between Dr. Cowdry, E.B. Smith, and Commissioner of Immigration re letter certifying Dr. Cowdry's son born in U.S.A. for reentry into country, 1927 June 2-July 8
    - E.B. Smith/Cowdry re lab budget for 1927-1928, 1927 June 29
    - Cowdry/E.B. Smith, thank you for letter to Commissioner of Immigration and request for additional lab space, 1927 July 6
    - Exchange between Cowdry, E.B. Smith and Barney Lupinek re granting additional lab space to Cowdry, requests for adjustments with Enclosure: Sketch of lab, and correspondence re work on rooms for Cowdry's new suite, 1927 August 1-29
    - List of expenditures for equiping Rooms 309-310, C.B. [Central Building] for Dr. Cowdry, 1927 October 18
    - Exchange between Dr. Cowdry, E.B. Smith, Professor Nicolle, E.C.C., H.O. re cost of engravings for Cowdry's two Heartwater Papers in Archiv de l'Institut Pasteur de Tunis and JEM, August 1925, Vol 42, No. 2 and in the Studies, 1927 November 27 1917 December 3-6 1928 March 22
    - Exchange re supplementary funds for Cowdry's budget 1927-28 w/S. Flexner approval of, 1928 February 16-March 1
    - [S. Flexner?] /Cowdry. Evaluation of Dr. Cowdry personally and professionally on leaving RIMR, 1928 April 13
    - [S. Flexner?] /Cowdry. Congratulations on new appointment and re Cavell and Scott, 1928 May 11
    - E.V. Cowdry/Francis G. Blake. Letter of resignation as Associate Member, RIMR, as of Aug 31, 1928 to Professor of Cytology, Washington University Medical School, St. Louis, Mo, 1928 June 6
    - Exchange between Cowdry/E.B. Smith re S. Flexner approval of Cowdry taking table incubator box to Saint Louis, 1928 July 31 1928 August 3
    - [Copy]. Cowdry/S. Flexner re Noguchi memorial service at University of Chicago?, 1928 November 22
    - Exchange between Cowdry/E.B. Smith re Cowdry becoming a naturalized citizen of U.S.A., 1930 February-March 31
    - Herald Tribune, "Sees Lung Cancer Mortality Rising". Newspaper clipping re Cowdry's statement at opening (Sept 8) of 14th Annual Conference of the Institutum Divi Thomae, a Roman Catholic Medical Research organization in Cincinnati, 1953 September 9
- Reports, 2
  - "Communications from Dr. E.V. Cowdry and Sir Arnold Theiler Relating to Dr. Cowdry's Work at the Transvaal University College in Pretoria". 3 duplicated copies containing Dr. Cowdry/ S. Flexner communications of 1924 Nov 11, 17 and S.A. Theiler/Flexner, 1924 Nov 5 re scientific work by Cowdry in South Africa (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - "Report by Dr. E.V. Cowdry Work Done Under Special Appropriation for Study un the Auspices of the Dept of Agriculture of the Union of South Africa in the Acceptance of an Invitation by Sir Arnold Theiler", 1925 April 18 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes 2 duplicated copies of report pp 95-99 and 6 pp of illustrations (pp 100-105) dealing with these studies. Also includes a working copy with corrections of report.